A Guide to the Shanks Family Papers, 1824-1853
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Shanks Family Papers, 1824-1853
The Library of Virginia
22022
9 leaves and 34 pages
Shanks Family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased from John Reynoldson Butterworth, DeWitt, Virginia, 1942.
Biographical Information
Born about 1783, Robert Shanks emigrated with his wife Elizabeth (b. ca. 1795) from Ireland and settled in Petersburg, Virginia. A carpenter, he acquired property in Petersburg and the surrounding counties of Chesterfield, Prince George and Surry. Robert Shanks died 21 July 1871, about 2 1/2 months after Elizabeth died 12 April 1871. They had at least five children, including Robert Shanks, Jr. (d. 1849) who also speculated in land.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1824-1853, of the Shanks family of Petersburg, Virginia, consisting of deeds for property in Petersburg, and in Chesterfield, Prince George, and Surry Counties, and Richmond, Virginia; agreements concerning sale of land in Surry County and in Petersburg; correspondence regarding deeds, construction work, powers of attorney, insurance claims, bonds, and a bill of purchase; and a contract for the construction of a dam.
Contents List
- Deed, dated 21 October 1824 and recorded 18 November 1824, for a lot in Petersburg from Alden B. Spooner (ca. 1786-1853) to Robert Shanks (1783-1871), both of Petersburg.
- Agreement, 1 January 1833, between George Evelyn Harrison (1797-1838) of Prince George County, Virginia, and Shanks concerning land in Surry County, Virginia.
- Deed, dated 23 March 1833 and recorded 11 June 1833, for a lot in Petersburg from William M. (d. 1849) and Rebecca Atkinson of Petersburg to Shanks.
- Deed, dated 27 July 1833 and recorded 16 February 1835, for certain land in Prince George County from Nathaniel J. Marks (d. 1871) of Prince George County to Robert Shanks.
- Deed, dated 22 October 1836, for certain land in Chesterfield County, Virginia, from Shanks and his wife Elizabeth Shanks (ca. 1795-1871) to Thomas Bragg of Petersburg.
- Deed, dated 8 December 1835 and recorded 9 December 1836, for a lot in Petersburg from Richard Whaites to Shanks.
- Deed, dated 16 November 1836 and recorded 27 March 1837, for 220 acres in Surry County from Benjamin Collier of Surry County to Shanks.
- Deed, dated 12 February 1836 and recorded 27 March 1837, for 283 acres in Surry County from John and Susan McAllister of Surry County to Shanks.
- Contract, 12 June 1837, between Shanks and D. W. Waring, general agent of Mechanic's Manufacturing Company for the construction of a dam.
- Bill of sale, 19 May 1841, from Shanks to James S. Foley for 1580 acres in Surry County.
- Deed, dated 11 March 1842 and recorded in Petersburg 11 March 1842, in Chesterfield County 14 March 1843, and in Prince George County, 10 May 1842, for a lot in Petersburg from Shanks to James May (1798-1873) and John Fitzhugh May (1784-1856) of Petersburg.
- Deed, dated and recorded 5 October 1842, for certain land from John F. May to Hugh Dooner of Petersburg.
- Deed, dated 3 May 1847 and recorded in Petersburg 12 May 1847, in Surry County 14 June 1847, for 1583 acres in Surry County from David May (ca. 1795-1870) and William Waverly Townes (1819-1869) to Robert Shanks, Jr. (d. 1849), all of Petersburg.
- Deed, dated and recorded 23 November 1847, for a lot in Richmond, Virginia, between Thomas Baxter of Petersburg, party of the first part, James C. (d. 1856) and A. Judson Crane of Richmond, party of the second part, and William Henry and Thomas Baxter, Henry, John, and George G. Exall, party of the third part.
- Letter, 6 December 1847, from William P. Underwood of Surry County to Shanks, Jr. concerning deeds
- Agreement, 1 November 1848, between Shanks, Jr., and Joel Sturdivant (1808-1852) of Petersburg for the sale of a lot in Petersburg.
- Letter, 10 June 1849, from Y. B. of Petersburg to [Benjamin?] Collier of Dinwiddie County, Virginia, concerning construction work on Collier's house and farm.
- Deed, dated 24 September 1849 and recorded 10 December 1849, for 502 acres in Surry County from David May and Alden B. Spooner, trustees of Edward Banks to Shanks.
- Letter, 20 December 1849, from John Rutherfoord (1792-1866) of Richmond and agent of the Mutual Assurance Society to David May concering deeds, power of attorney, and an insurance claim.
- Letter, 13 January 1853, from A. Hopkins of Surry County to David May concerning some bonds.
- Letter, 1 April 1853, from Davenport and Allen and Company of Richmond to Shanks enclosing a bill of purchase.